Finding Aid for the Charles Madison Sarratt material
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Charles Madison Sarratt material
undated
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0353
9.18 linear feet
- Admission Recommendations (Box 1)
- Advice to Students (Box 1)
- Alumni, representative list, 1965 (Box 1)
- Alumni Official Business (Box 1)
- Alumnus magazine, March-April 1961 (Box 1)
- Biographical Sketch (Box 1)
- Calendars, 1966 and 1967 (Box 1)
- Clippings, miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Commission on Human Relations (Box 1)
- Committee on Wills (Box 1)
- Committee Service (Box 1)
- Correspondence, including congratulatory letters on appointment to Vice-Chancellorship, James Lawson case, University correspondence, and notes of appreciation (Box 1)
- Donation letters (Box 1)
- "Echoes of Dudley Stadium" 4 phonograph records (Box 1)
- Esso Education Foundation In-Service Institute: “Mathematics reltated to other Sciences” (Box 1)
- Film: Sarratt & Heard (Box 1)
- Buck Green at Vanderbil (removed to film case) (Box 1)
- 3 (removed to film case) (Box 1)
- Norman Goldberg, notes on (Box 2)
- Guestbook, 1957-1965 (16 pages) (Box 2)
- Gym-non-athletic (Box 2)
- Honor System brochure (Box 2)
- Invitations (Box 2)
- Keys - 5 in envelope. Alumni Hall basement, Mem. Gym, Filing cabinet (Box 2)
- James Lawson case - clippings (Box 2)
- Lecture notes in Math (Box 2)
- Medicine (Box 2)
- Metropolitan Youth Commissions (Box 2)
- Nashville Academy of Medicine (Box 2)
- National Collegiate Athletic Association 1948 yearbook (Box 2)
- Cobb Pilcher: In Memorium, 1940 (Box 2)
- Phonograph records: removed from files (Box 2)
- "Your Neighbor", 12/6/52 (Box 2)
- "Living Endowment", 11/6/59 (Box 2)
- Profile of Vanderbilt 1956-76 volumes 1 & 2 (Box 2)
- Requiem (Box 2)
- Report to Chancellor (Box 2)
- Southeastern Conference (Box 2)
- Special Prospects (Box 2)
- Speeches, notes (Box 2)
- Student Center (Box 2)
- Sympathy (Box 2)
- Tennessee College Association: Proceedings of the 37th and 38th meeting (Box 2)
- Vanderbilt University material, mostly concerning Sarratt; brochures, publications (Box 2)
- Contents of Dean Sarratt's Office
  - Sarratt
    - Egypt Throughout the Ages
    - Craige: Cannibal Cousins, (1934)
    - Publication: Centennial of Llirestone College, (1945)
    - Pederson: Regional Planning for Social Work Education, (1949)
    - Gauss: Life in College, (1930)
    - Eliot: Scenes of Clerical Life
    - Conant: Modern Science & Modern Man, (1952)
    - Keppel: The undergraduate and his College, (1917)
    - Kelly: The American Arts College, (1925)
    - Pressy, et al., Research Adventures in University Teaching, (1928)
    - Payne and Spleth: Open Letter to College Teachers, (1935)
    - Funkhouser: Arts and Sciences, (1947)
    - Book: How to Succeed in College, (1927)
    - Farrington: Railroading from the Rear End, (1946)
    - Howes: Twenty Years Among the Twenty-Year Olds, (1929)
    - State of Tennessee: Tennessee Blue Book, (1949-50)
    - White: Messages of Governors of Tennessee (Vol. 7), (1967)
    - Sarratt: Arithmetic Manual, (1924)
    - Mims: The Christ of the Poets, (1948)
    - Alexander: Thomas A. R. Nelson of East Tennessee, (1956)
    - Bowe: Tax Planning for Estates, (1949)
    - McAllister: Inside the campus, (1958)
    - Rietz & Crathorne: College Algebra, (1919)
    - Huddleston: Problems of College Education
    - Meredith: Eva Harrington, (1922)
    - Shakespeare: Midsummer Night’s Dream
    - Hamlet
    - The Tampest
    - King Henry IV
    - Austen: Pride and Prejudice, (1914)
    - Kirkpatrick: American College, (1926)
    - Ames: The New Orthodoxy, (1918)
    - Rice: Sonnets, (1921)
    - Thoreau: A Week on the Concord and Merrimac Rivers, (1921)
    - Eliot: Silas Marner
    - Bocher: Higher Algebra, (1912)
    - Russell: Education and the Good Life, (1926)
    - Morris & Brown: Differential Equations, (1938)
    - Roberts: The Great Locamotive Chase, (1956)
    - Miller: Popular Mathematics, (1942)
    - Hoyt: The Vanderbilts and their Fortunes, (1962)
    - Nemkoff: Marriage and the Family, (1947)
    - Green: Sociology, (1952)
    - Corrington: Applied Mathematics, (1943)
    - McKissick: Men and Women of Carolina, (1948)
    - Armitage: Operations Santa Fe, (1948)
    - Colyer: Life and Times of Andrew Jackson, Vols. I & II, (1904)
    - Turner: An Adventure in Alumni Relations, (1947)
    - (Published by V .U. and personally enscribed to Mr. Sarratt)
    - Williams: Golden Treasury of Best Songs, (1953)
    - Knight: Public Education in the South, (1922)
    - (Enscribed by the author to Dr. Edwin Mims)
    - Foerster and Pierson: American Ideals, (1917)
    - (Has Edwin Mims' name on it)
    - Rostand: Cyrano De Bergerac, (1899)
    - (Has C.P. Mims name in it)
    - Brète: Aimer Quand Même, (1930)
    - Romains: Knoch, (1927)
    - Daudet: La Belle-Nivernaise, (1938)
    - Maupassant: Six Contes Choisis, (1936)
    - Victor Hugo: Selections, (1893)
    - (Has "Edwin Mims, Jr., Chapel Hill, N.C., June 6, 1912) enscribed)
    - Daudet: Sapho, Manon Lescant
    - Book of Proverbs
    - Moffatt: The New Testament
    - The Holy Scriptures
    - Law, ed.: Romeo & Juliet, (1916)
    - Holy Bible (Mary Honstone, Fall 1918, AOTT)
    - Scott: Ivanhoe, (1898)
    - (Has John Elliott Sloan, Wallace School, 1917, written on 1st page)
    - Thackeray: Roundabout Papers, (1882)
    - Peabody: Sunday Evenings in College Chapel, (1911)
    - Rauschenbusch: Social Principles of Jesus, (1916)
    - Saint Exupery: Vol de Nuit, (1939)
    - Williams: The Aneid of Virgil, (1910)
    - Yearbook of Agriculture, 1956: Animal Diseases
    - Morris & Brown: Differential Equations, (1942)
    - State of Tennessee: Messages of Governors, Vol. V, (1959)
    - Barrie: My Lady Nicotine
    - Oursler: Why I Know There Is a God, (1950)
    - Foust: The Soviet World in Flux, (1966)
    - Peter: The Green Lines of Summer (#20 signed by author)
    - Naylor: Impact of the Computer on Society, (1966)
    - Machlis: The Enjoyment of Music
    - Peabody: Jesus Christ and the Social Question, (1906)
    - Gouwens: The Stirred Nest, (1933)
    - Gibbs: Collected Works (Vol. 1), (1928)
    - Nye: Knowledge is Power, (1956)
    - State of Tennessee: Messages of Governors, Vol. VI
    - Olmstead: Arnold's Practical Commentary, (1949)
    - Garner, Robert L.: This is the Way It Was (personally enscribed to Mr. Sarratt by the author)
    - Irish and Prothro: The Politics of American Democracy, (1959)
    - Hand, Learned: The Spirit of Liberty, (1952)
    - Hart: College Algebra, (1938)
    - Love: calculus, (1916)
    - NCAA: 1948 yearbook
    - Caldwell: Duck’s Back, (1952)
    - Muir: The Theory of Determinants, (1911)
    - Carmichael: Groups of Finite Order, (1937)
    - Kalpinski: History of Arithmetic, (1925)
    - (enscribed from Prof. J. T. McGill to Madison Sarratt)
    - Douglas: 50 Year Bibliography of Medical Works
    - Conkwright: Differential Equations, (1934)
    - Webster's Dictionary, (1939)
    - McMillan: History of Limestone College, (1970)
    - American Men of Science, (1938)
    - Herbert: The Secret Battle, (1920)
    - Henry: Rolling Stones, (1919)
    - Henry: Heart of the West, (1919)
    - Long: American Patriotic Prose, (1917)
    - (has written on 1st page: “Walter Clyde Curry, V.U., 1918”)
    - Byrne: Messer Marco Polo, (1921)
    - Scott: The lady of the Lake, (1928)
    - Hagen: Historical Essays by Lord MacAulay, (1921)
    - Huxley: Brave New Work Revisited, (1958)
    - Byron: Poems
    - Streeter: Window on America, (1959)
    - Birch: The Lay of the Nibelungers, (1887)
    - Shakespear: Romeo and Juliet
    - Wells: Merrill Moore, (1955)
    - Duncan, editor: The Humanities in Higher Education in the South (report of a conference held at V.U., 1944)
    - Scott: Ivanhoe, (1900)
    - Butler: The Way of All Flesh, (1935)
    - Stevenson: An Inland Voyage
    - Northcott: Mathematics of Finance, (1946)
    - Kells: Elementary Differential Equations, (1935)
    - Browning, Robert: Poems and Plays, (1922)
    - Gates, ed.: Selections from Matthew Arnold, (1897)
    - Lamb: Tales from Shakespeare
    - Alden: English Verse
    - (Many notes in Eddie Mims' handwriting)
    - Teter: One Hundred Narrative Poems, (1918)
    - Tennyson: In Manoriam, (1912)
    - Browning: Selections, (1899)
    - Dickens: A Tale of Two Cities
    - Patten, ed.: Great Short Stories, (1906)
    - Thackecy: Henry Esmond
    - Fredericks: The Ivory Snuff Box, (1912)
    - Wills: Early and Late, (1959)
    - Zerfoss: Within One’s Self Worlds Lie Unborn (Personal inscription by the author to Mr. Sarratt)
    - Matthew Arnold: Selections, (1897)
    - Service: The Spell of the Yukon, (1907)
    - Walker: Selected English Short Stories, (1915)
    - Jones, Richard, ed.: Shakespeare's The Merchant of Venice, (1904)
    - Muir: Theory of Determinants, Vol. I, (1907)
    - Wilson: The Parthenon of Pericles and Its Reproduction in America, 1937
    - Chaffin, Nora C.: Trinity College, 1839-1892, 1950
    - Stuber: How We Got Our Denomination, 1959
    - Cole: Sex and Love in the Bible, 1959
    - Stevenson, R.L.: Familiar Studies of Men and Books
    - Cooper: The last of the Mohicans
    - Stieglitz, ed.: Chemistry in Medicine, 1928
    - Weber: History of Philosophy, 1897
    - Hamilton: Selections from Writings of A. Lincoln, 1922
    - Moulton: Isaiah, 1897
    - Daudet: Tartar in de Tarascon
    - Cohen: Differential Equations, 1933
    - Browne: The Wisdom of Israel, 1945
    - Mackender: Britain and the British Seas, 1907
    - Who's Who in America: Vol. 18 (1934-35)
    - Who's Who in America: Vol. 22 (1942-43)
    - Ludwig: The Nile, 1937
    - 1 packet Nashville Banner reprints, April 7, 1967
    - 1 envelope of paid bills, letters from family, etc.
    - 1 box of photographs, Sarratt, and family snapshots.
    - Prospectus for Camp Mondamin, 1941 season, with pictures of Sarratt
    - Prospectus for Camp Mondamin, 1941 season, with pictures of Sarratt
    - 2 photographs of Dean Sarratt's home
    - 3 reproduced photographs, possibly Sarratt's fore people
    - File folder, speech to Chamber of Ocrrmerce re: O. C. Carmichael
    - 1 very old file folder with mementos of life at Syracuse University, (1915)
    - American Scientist, vol. 36, #4 (1948)
    - 1 packet marked "Insurance papers, all kinds, C. M. Sarratt and Houston Sarratt.
    - 1 packet marked "Income Tax Matters", C.M. Sarratt
    - 1 envelope "key to box (file, metal) in bookcase—my will"
    - 1 envelope, "social security"
    - 1 envelope, sealed, "loan to P.D. Houston"
    - 1 envelope, personal family photographs
    - 1 file folder: "CMS Insurance"
    - 1 envelope: "cost of education of Houston Sarratt, Jr. & Dennis Sarratt"
    - 1 envelope: "Odds & Ends" — mainly insurance correspondence
    - 1 envelope: "1961 income tax"
    - 1 envelope: "1969 income tax"
    - 1 envelope: "1959-60 income tax
    - 1 envelope: 1966 correspondence with income tax people
    - 1 envelope: Bank statements & returned checks, Sarratt family
    - Income tax returns for, 1969 and 1979
    - Envelope: "1971 income tax"
    - Envelope: "1965 income tax"
    - 1 desk weight "Alabama Polytechnic"
    - 1 desk weight "The Original Sigma Nu Rock"
    - 1 coin 45th reunion, Cornell University
    - 1 1961 United Givers Fund award, broken
    - 1 small trophy
    - 1 note card tray
    - 1 wooden "thingamajig"
    - 1 letter, opened, "Sam Fleming & O.H. Ingram honoring Edwin Graig & Eldon Stevenson, Jr., May 3, 1963"
    - 2 plastic door plates: "Dean of Alumni Madison Sarratt"
    - 1 ash tray "Morristown, Tennessee"
    - 1 address book
    - 1 statuette—Commodore
    - 1 personal size file cabinet (metal, green) containing personal items from college days and early financial matters
    - 2 envelopes marked 1969 Inocme Tax
    - 1 envelope marked 1970 Income Tax
    - 1 file folder 1968 taxes
    - 1 file folder, 1967 taxes
    - 1 file folder 1974 tax
    - Packet: letters re: Death of Frances Allen (sister)
    - Christmas cards from fimeds; sympathy cards, personal notes from family
    - 1 packet marked "C.M. Sarratt private (personal) papers. No official papers" containing financial matters, photo, clippings, and correspondence with regard to an honorary degree awarded by University of the South.
    - 1 packet "Invariant theory notes and reprints on determinants"
    - 1 packet containing Dean Sarratt’s payroll stubs, 2 copies of the Vanderbilt Alunnus, and a wallet.
    - Little: Marcus Fabius Quintilianus (1951) Vols. I & II enscribed to Dean Sarratt frcm President Robb of Peabody
    - Ford: A First Course in the Differential and Integral Calculus, 1928
    - Davidson, Donald: Report on a Study of the Honor System (1944) V.U.
    - Porter: In Wildness Is the Preservation of the World, 1962
    - Thoreau: Reflections at Walden
    - McQuade, ed.: Schoolhouse
    - Furikhouser: The Days That Are Gone. Enscribed by the author to Sarratt.
    - Gibran: The Prohpet
    - Rome & the Vatican
    - Jacobs: 102 Years, a Story of the School of Engineering, 1975
    - Purdue: Papers Pertaining to the Confederacy
    - Homes of Tennessee
    - McGaw: A Brief History of Vanderbilt University (Enscribed to Dean Sarratt by author)
    - Envelope from U.S. Treasure Dept, to Sarratt
    - Envelope: 1962 Income Tax
    - Envelope: 1964 Income Tax
    - A Treasure of old envelopes, complete with Postage, none of them cancelled: 38 2C envelopes, 39 3C envelopes, 4 4C envelopes, 1 6C air mail envelope, 2 1C postcards.
    - 1 envelope, "Financial"
    - 1 leather carry case
    - 2 boxes personalized stationery
    - 1 box misc. stationery and Christmas cards "frcm the Dean"
    - 2 desk weights, "Union of Louisville"
    - 1 "coin", University of the South
    - 1 "coin", State of Mississippi sesquicentennial
    - 1 "coin", State of Mississippi sesquicentennial
    - 1 desk weight, “Kissam Hall“
    - Envelope: "1963 inccme tax"
    - 1 basketball trophy
    - 1 desk weight "30 million for Vanderbilt—Vice-Chairman, 1960-62"
    - 2 desk pens with mounts
    - 1 framed certificate: Vanderbiltia Sodalitas Nashvillensis (Nashville Vanderbilt Club)
    - 1 framed tribute from Board of Trust, May 6, 1966
    - 1 framed Service to Mankind Award (Sertoma)
    - 1 framed Vanderbilt certificate, 55 Million for V.U. campaign
    - 1 wall plaque. National Football Foundation Hall of Fame
    - 1 wall plaque, 30 Million for V.U. campaign
    - 1 wall plaque Limestone College
- Vanderbilt
  - Publication: Profile of Vanderbilt U. 1956-76, volumes 1 & 2
  - Publication: Esso Education Foundation In-service Institute, Professors Bryant & Wesson, 1960
  - mathematics Related to the other Science: Esso Ed. Found.
  - Publication: David Lipscomb College brochure, 1962
  - Publication: Honor System Brochures, 12 copies
  - In Memoriam: Cobb Pilcher (1949), published by Vanderbilt University
  - National Collegiate Athletic Ass’n: 1948 Yearbook (Dean Sarratt’s report @ p. 34)
  - Hill Turner: An Adventure in Alumni Relations, 1947
  - V.U.: Proceedings of the Semi-Centenhial of Vanderbilt University, 1875-1925
  - Dean Sarratt's calendar for, 1966
  - Dean Sarratt's calendar for, 1967
  - Representative list of Alumni, (1965)
  - V .U.: Alunmi Directory, 1923
  - V. U.: Inauguration of O. C. Carmichael, (1938)
  - V.U.: Inauguration of O.C. Carmichael (1938) (complete with gold jacket)
  - Proceedings of 37th meeting of Tennessee College Association (address by Dean Sarratt)
  - Proceedings of 38th meeting of Tennessee College Association, (1959)
  - Lecture notes in Math (2 notebooks)
  - 1 looseleaf notebook "Red Cross Carrnittees" of reports by Dean Sarratt to faculty, chancellor, etc.
  - packet, "Letters from Friends on my appointment as Vice-Chancellor" but containing University correspondence with faculty, etc.
  - 1 file folder of various correspondence and notes for speeches written on halves of envelopes, etc.
  - plastic carry case with files of speeches, as well as clippings and correspondence re: James Lawson case, and University correspondence
  - 1 guest book, signatures of visitors for, 1957-1965
  - 1 file folder with miscellaneous correspondence
  - Report of the vice-chancellor to the chancellor, June 7, 1946
  - 1 copy of Vanderbilt Alunnus, March-April, 1956
  - 1 file folder of miscellaneous correspondence
  - 1 file folder, "Personal, C.M. Sarratt" biographical sketch
  - 1 file folder "Gym - nan-athletic"
  - Film: "Buck Green at Vanderbilt", 1926
  - '1 key marked "Alunni Hall Basement"
  - 'l key marked "Master Key, Man - Gym"
  - 2 filing cabinet keys
  - 1 unmarked key
  - 1 box clippings fron newspapers, correspondence (same historically valuable to Archives), speeches
  - 2 copies, phonograph record: "Living Endowment Area Chairmen's Conference 11/6/59" speech by Sarratt, Purdy, others.
  - 2 phonograph records, "Your Neighbor", 12/6/52
  - 2 phonograph records, "Your Neighbor", 12/6/52
  - 2 phonograph records, "Your Neighbor", 12/6/52
  - copies phonograph record Gabriel "Echoes of Dudley Stadium"
  - 2 boxes personalized stationery
  - Campus telephone directories for, 1973, 1966, 1963, 1965
  - 1951 General Catalogue V. U. --Dean Sarratt 1 s name embosserl
  - 1 film marked “3”
  - General Catalogue V. U. -Dean Sarratt’s name embossed
  - File folders in green paper file cabinet
    - Alunni Official Business
    - Alunni Official Business
    - Recommendation for Admission
    - Recommendation for Admission
    - Appreciation notes & lectures
    - Addresses empty folder
    - Advice to Students
    - Sarratt Center
    - Sarratt Center
    - Comm on Human Relations
    - Committee Service
    - Comnittee on Wills
    - Donation letters
    - Film: Sarratt & Heard
    - Miscellaneous
    - Speeches
    - Invitation
    - Metropolitan Youth Commission
    - Miscellaneous
    - Medicine
    - Nash. Academy of Medicine
    - Requiem
    - Sympathy
    - Special Prospects
    - Student Center
    - Southeastern Conference
    - 3 framed pictures, "Full Speed," "Wing over Wing," and "To Starboard" marked on back "Property of Jane Sutherland"
    - 1 framed picture 1955 Gator Bowl champions
    - 1 framed photo, 1937 SIC champions (basketball)
    - 1 framed photo, 1961 meeting Grand Rapids Vanderbilt Club
    - 1 framed Vanderbilt War Dead WWII
    - 1 framed Vanderbilt University Honor Roll WWI